<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lady's religion In a letter to the Honourable my Lady Howard. By a divine of the Church of England. With a prefatory epistle to the same lady, by a lay-gentleman.</title>
            <author>Divine of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212982</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825529</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29913</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48131)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29913)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2188:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lady's religion In a letter to the Honourable my Lady Howard. By a divine of the Church of England. With a prefatory epistle to the same lady, by a lay-gentleman.</title>
                  <author>Divine of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Warren for Richard Baldwin, at the Oxford-Arms in Warwick-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The prefatory epistle is signed: Adeisidæmon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Lambeth Palace Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christianity --  Essence, genius, nature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian ethics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29913:1"/>
            <p>A LADY's RELIGION IN A LETTER To the Honourable My Lady <hi>Howard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Divine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a Prefatory Epiſtle to the ſame Lady, By a Lay-Gentleman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Warren</hi> for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> at the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-lane,</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29913:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29913:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Never read any thing with more pleaſure and ſatisfaction than the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious <hi>Letter of Religion</hi> addreſs'd to your Ladyſhip. The Author's noble deſign, and happy method of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, could add nothing to the value I always had for his great Learning, Candor, and Ingenuity. But to find his performance approv'd by a
<pb facs="tcp:29913:3"/>Perſon of your Ladyſhip's extraordinary Judgment and Vertues, has, I own, very conſiderably increas'd my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration for him.</p>
            <p>If my Opinion is of any weight with your Ladyſhip, I think he has ſhewn Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be plain, ſhort, and intelligible, according to thoſe very rules by which he tries its orthodoxy: And that the knowledge of it depends not upon the helps of Spurious Learning, he has with a deal of genuine Learning
<pb facs="tcp:29913:3"/>demonſtrated. What ought to recomend him moſt, is, that although he be a Divine, yet he pretends not to make any thing paſs upon you by vertue of the bare Authority of his Profeſſion; but he modeſtly writes as an unprejudic'd Perſon, what he believes any other had a right of doing, whom your Ladyſhip would pleaſe to honour with her Commands.</p>
            <p>'Tis now extremely rare to meet with Learning, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and Integrity, united
<pb facs="tcp:29913:4"/>in one Perſon; as we find 'em in our Friend. For Learning is frequently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Prejudices, Big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotry and Pride; Freedom of thought turns into Licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onſneſs, when 'tis not guided by knowledge; and we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive moſt Men every day ſacrifice both Learning and Liberty to their Intereſt. But what's of more fatal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence is, That ſeveral who have the Reputation of thoſe Endowments, are the fartheſt in the World from poſſeſſing them. Learning, for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,
<pb facs="tcp:29913:4"/>is a term of great Ambiguity. True <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> conſiſts <hi>in the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of things as they are in themſelves, and the expreſſing of this Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in proper words whereby it is convey'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the minds of others.</hi> To this a right <hi>Method</hi> indeed is neceſſary, but <hi>Elegance</hi> only accidental.</p>
            <p>This is a natural and eaſy notion; but did it univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally obtain, <hi>Learning</hi> would become more common than is
<pb facs="tcp:29913:5"/>compatible with ſome Mens intereſt. To fruſtrate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all its native and uſeful effects, <hi>Learning</hi> muſt be made to conſiſt in ſtrange and difficult words, in the meer Grammatical Knowledge of Languages, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the ſenſe, if ſometimes they have any; in frivolous, precarious, and impertinent diſtinctions; in Etymologies, a World of old ſtories, and the Lord knows what Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beriſh and Non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſenſe. This the truely Learned call <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantry.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29913:5"/>
            <p>But your Ladiſhip being apt to think others can have no indirect deſigns no more than your ſelf, may imagine that this falſe Notion could never be induſtriouſly promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but might be only the prevailing effect of caſual Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in certain places and times. I ſhan't trouble you now, Madam, with a Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical account of the matter; but I beg of you to conſider two or three things which may be capable of undeceiving a leſs diſcerning Perſon. This
<pb facs="tcp:29913:6"/>kind of Learning, in the firſt place, being attain'd with mighty difficulty, very few of either Sex have the Patience, or the leiſure to ſtudy for it; and ſo moſt of the World are oblig'd to take it at ſecond hand from others, who never think themſelves over-paid in conſideration of their pains or merit. Be pleas'd next to remember, that the ignorant are no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Judges of Learning, and that all thoſe who are not Men of Art being ignorant, muſt therefore never pretend
<pb facs="tcp:29913:6"/>to queſtion or contradict any thing the Learned ſay; much leſs may they take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 'em to teach or inſtruct others. Now, Madam, if you don't think this Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of being excluſively of all others the only Men of Learning, the only allow'd Teachers, and the only Judges of what they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do teach, to be a form'd deſign; if you don't think it as dextrouſly manag'd as any other joint-ſtock, or monopoly in the World; if you don't think the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages
<pb facs="tcp:29913:7"/>worth the pains of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving the Scheme; I'm content to loſe your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's good Opinion, which I prefer to that of all the Learned in Four Ages I could name, adding the majority of ſuch as are now ſo accounted.</p>
            <p>There's nothing more obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than that this artful Learning deſtroys all <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of courſe; and as for <hi>Integrity,</hi> they are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent, as Paint and Beauty: for our Learned Guide muſt
<pb facs="tcp:29913:7"/>be always telling us that he labours for our information; ſo far at leaſt, he muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement us for our Patience and Money. But that he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe intends, our ſlow proficiency aſſures us; Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alſo does convince us that 'tis againſt his intereſt we ſhould improve, for ſo in time he grows uſeleſs; and he often blabs out the ſecret himſelf when he tells us that what he ſays is unintelligible, and not to be apprehended by us in this World; whatever we may
<pb facs="tcp:29913:8"/>do in the next. How Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion has thriv'd, or is like to do ſo under ſuch manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I need not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly deſcribe to your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; who more readily ſees all the conſequences, than many others can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the thing it ſelf.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Religion</hi> is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern of all, ſo our Author ſhews the ſtudy of it to be the buſineſs of every body; and that nothing can be true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which Poverty, want
<pb facs="tcp:29913:8"/>of Letters, particular Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, or any condition of Life can hinder us from acquiring. Wherein this Excellent and moſt divine Religion (which depends not upon certain forms, times, perſons or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) does conſiſt, I ſhan't re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat out of the Letter which you have already perus'd; but give it you in the words of <hi>Minutius Felix,</hi> the moſt Eloquent of the Chriſtian A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologiſts. <hi>Do you think,</hi> ſays he to the Idolaters, <hi>that we conceal what we adore, becauſe we have no Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb facs="tcp:29913:9"/>nor Altars? For what Image can I frame of God, when, if you rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, Man himſelf is his Image? What</hi> Temple <hi>ſhall I build for him, when the whole Univerſe, which he has made, is not able to contain him? And when I that am but a Man, can command a larger habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall I confine the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Divine Majeſty within one ſmall ſhrine? Should we not rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate a</hi> Temple <hi>to him in our Minds, and conſecrate
<pb facs="tcp:29913:9"/>an</hi> Altar <hi>for him in our hearts? Shall I offer thoſe things in Victims and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſices to the Lord, which he has created for my</hi> uſe; <hi>ſcornfully throwing back his</hi> gifts <hi>to himſelf again? This were Ingratitude; when the moſt pleaſing</hi> Sacrifices <hi>to him are a</hi> good diſpoſition, <hi>a</hi> pure mind, <hi>and a</hi> ſincere Conſcience. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever therefore keeps himſelf</hi> Innocent, <hi>he prays to the Lord; He that loves</hi> Justice, <hi>does offer him</hi> Sacrifice; <hi>whoever abſtains
<pb facs="tcp:29913:10"/>from</hi> fraud, <hi>procures the</hi> favour <hi>of God; and he that delivers any out of</hi> diſtreſs, <hi>makes him an agreeable</hi> offering. <hi>Theſe are our</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, <hi>this is our</hi> Divine Service: <hi>And he that is the</hi> honeſtest Man <hi>among us, him we alſo count the moſt</hi> Religious.</p>
            <p>Are not theſe, Madam, are not theſe moſt charming and Heavenly Expreſſions? Here's the deſcription of a <hi>Religion</hi> truly becoming the Dignity and Goodneſs of the Divine
<pb facs="tcp:29913:10"/>Nature. 'Tis as general as Mankind; not varied by their different Languages, Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or Cuſtoms; and as much the interest of all in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, as it muſt be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of every honest Man to obſerve it.</p>
            <p>Now if true <hi>Learning</hi> be nothing elſe, as I ſaid, <hi>but the knowledge of things properly expreſs'd,</hi> (and of this, Madam, you ſhow your Sex to be very capable) I ſee no reaſon why all Men indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently ſhould not as lawfully
<pb facs="tcp:29913:11"/>teach, as they are bound to practiſe, their Religion. Why <hi>Women</hi> likewiſe may not enjoy the privilege of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Religious duties, which they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to practiſe themſelves, I want <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ll to be enform'd. They have the ſame Senſes of Seeing and H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aring with us, they have the ſame Faculties of Thinking and Speaking, they learn to read and write with the ſame Facility, they equally underſtand the noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Virtue and Vice, of Diſrepute and Honour, of
<pb facs="tcp:29913:11"/>Wiſdom and Folly; they are as much concern'd, as we are for their own happineſs, as well as that of their Friends; and will be ſo for that of all Mankind, when they conſider themſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to contribute towards the preſervation of the whole, in the good whereof their own is involv'd. Some Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have left behind them Illuſtrious Monuments of their Invention, Knowledge, and Courage; and what particular perſons have done, 'tis poſſible for the generality
<pb facs="tcp:29913:12"/>of the Species to do, or more. Nor can I perceive any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between us, but that of Sex and Education; and to whom the defects of the latter are to be imputed, any Man would bluſh to relate that is concern'd for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or juſtice of our kind. The particular care your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip has taken to inform a great many of your poor ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Neighbour's Minds, as well as to feed and cover their Bodies, is a Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration that the duty of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction may be as ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="tcp:29913:12"/>perform'd by your Sex, as that of Charity or good works.</p>
            <p>I don't underſtand you right, Madam, or I need not beg your Pardon for publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this little piece without your privity or permiſſion. <hi>Reaſon,</hi> I know, is the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle</hi> that muſt decide this buſineſs: And there ſeems to be more reaſon for the liberty I have taken, than for our Author's compliance with your Ladyſhip's requeſt, tho' he was likewiſe in the right. He wrote nothing but what
<pb facs="tcp:29913:13"/>he was convinc'd you perfectly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood before, taught by the original di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of your own fruitful mind; ſo you receiv'd his admirable perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, rather as a mark of his reſpect, than a preſent you needed: therefore I preſume now to diſtribute it among thoſe of yours and my own Sex, who want ſuch an aſſiſtance from him: You en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy no perſon, I'm ſure, thoſe divine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of Body and Mind, whereof your Enemies (if you can have any) muſt own you are Miſtreſs; much leſs would you deprive others of the benefit they may receive from this Treatiſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the uſefulneſs of it to your ſelf was prevented by an excellent genius. That you may be ever happy, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, is the conſtant deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladyſhip's moſt Obſervant Friend and Admirer. <hi>ADEISID AEMON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29913:13"/>
            <head>A LADY's RELIGION.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce God has been pleas'd to incline your heart to an early and ſerious enquiry af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Religion, ſo that you are ſincerely deſirous to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29913:14"/>know the will of God, in order to do it, I heartily wiſh you had laid your Commands upon one more able to aſſiſt you, than I am: who, being bred up in an Age of Speculation and Controverſy, have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted my ſelf to the ſtudy of Divinity more perhaps than to the practice of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and have been (I pray God forgive me) more deſirous to furniſh my Head with Notions, than my Heart with good Inclinations. I thought
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29913:14"/>my ſelf, by my Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, chiefly engag'd in a ſtudy how to defend the Church by Law eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd againſt all Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, rather than to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the common cauſe of ſerious Piety; and whilſt by the ſtrange unaccount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able genius of this Age, I have been led aſide to mix the ſtudy of Politicks with that of Religion, I have been buſily aſſiſting the Office of a Miniſter of State, rather than doing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29913:15"/>the good work of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now although it has pleas'd God to make me in ſome meaſure ſenſible of thoſe By-paths, in which I have ſometimes walk'd, to the hindrance of that duty unto which I ought intirely to have devoted my ſelf; yet I am apt to fear leſt thoſe Prejudices and undue Prepoſſeſſions of Mind may ſtill remain within me, by which I ſhall be prevented from gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29913:15"/>your Ladyſhip ſuch an Idea of Religion, as is ſhort, plain, and pure, free from ſuperſtitious Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dages, and ſeparate from every by-intereſt.</p>
            <p>But without doubt ſuch as this is the true Spirit of the Chriſtian Religion, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very line whereof directly tends to make us eaſy within our ſelves, kind and comfortable to one another here, and happy with God hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29913:16"/>
            <p>That our holy Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is a wiſe Inſtitution, will be evident to any one who conſiders that God is its Author, whoſe Wiſdom appears in all his Works: Thus the frame of viſible nature being agreeably ſet together, and having each part of it ſuited to uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and proper ends, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrates it ſelf to be the work of divine Wiſdom: in like manner the whole Plan of pure Religion, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alſo its parts ſuitable
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29913:16"/>to each other, and every one of them agreeably ſet to the ſame good and great Deſign of the whole, does thereby prove it ſelf to be the contrivance of an All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe God.</p>
            <p>And hereby the Wiſdom of the Chriſtian Religion will particularly appear, becauſe every part of it tends to promote the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal good of Mankind; for which reaſon the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Founder thereof was nam'd <hi>Jeſus,</hi> (that is) <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:29913:17"/>becauſe his only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign was to ſave us from the prevailing power of Sin, and from thoſe Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in which that evil power would involve us.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Temperance</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes our Health, <hi>Juſtice</hi> in our dealings prevents us from ſuſtaining the reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the injur'd, and gains us truſt among Men, with all the benefits which ariſe from thence. <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> by promoting the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good of others draws
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29913:17"/>back their love and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to our ſelves, while <hi>Patience</hi> preſerves quiet within our own Breaſts, and <hi>Self-denial</hi> by reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our extravagant Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, eſtabliſhes the juſt power of Reaſon over us; thereby fitting us for all conditions of life; and thus the law of <hi>Chriſt</hi> anſwers to the Character of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by its agreeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the beſt deſign of God in the chiefeſt good of Man: and upon this account <hi>Solomon</hi> character'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29913:18"/>the Idea of Religion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Beſide theſe moral du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties there are ſeveral threats of God's Judgments and promiſes of his favour contain'd in Chriſt's Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution; the former were wiſely deſign'd to reſtrain us from Immoralities, which are our greateſt Follies; and the latter to engage us in the practice of Vertue, which is our greateſt Wiſdom: the threatnings prepare the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29913:18"/>way for the Promiſes, and qualify us to receive 'em; in as much as they ſhake off our affections from ill objects, in order for the Promiſes to fix them upon good ones. We muſt needs ceaſe to do evil, before we can learn to do well.</p>
            <p>Now although a due conſideration of the divine nature will carry us on to the belief of a future ſtate, in which he who is in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection the beſt of all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, will diſtinguiſh the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29913:19"/>good from the bad by am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple rewards and juſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments: yet becauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ones capacity may not be ſufficient to make this wiſe reflection, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was pleas'd (as the Goſpel phraſes it) <hi>to bring Life and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality to light: i. e.</hi> to give the World full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a future ſtate, in which the juſt God will diſtinguiſh Men hereafter in ſuch a manner as they ſhall diſtinguiſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves here; and 'tis the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29913:19"/>wiſdom of every one to preſerve this belief in his heart, and bear it always about him, becauſe 'tis the moſt awful Monitor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our committing fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yields the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt encouragement to Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
            <p>From what has been ſaid, your Ladyſhip ſees firſt what is meant by <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Soul,</hi> viz. to deliver it from vitious habits and fearful puniſhments, the fatal conſequents of ſuch
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29913:20"/>habits; and by eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Virtue therein to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend it to the favour of God. And ſecondly, that the Goſpel of Chriſt was deſign'd to this very end; and its tendency hereunto is its Wiſdom. And thirdly, from hence you alſo perceive in what reſpect Faith in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is ſaid to ſave us, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe this Faith is our receiving the Chriſtian Moral for the Rule of our lives, and the threats and Promiſes contain'd in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29913:20"/>Goſpel, for the outward motives of our practice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Rule.</p>
            <p>And from theſe three conſiderations, ſumm'd up together, you may exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all the various pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences which differing Churches and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons make to the purity of Chriſtian Faith, ſo as to form a right judgment of 'em; for that Communion which manifeſts it ſelf to have no other deſign than to aſſiſt its Members
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29913:21"/>in ſaving their Souls from the power of Sin by the Moral and Motives afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd, is certainly the pureſt Church; and that Faith which has no other tendency, is the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Faith. So that if you form your ſelf upon this Principle, you may paſs by all nice Speculations, or profound Myſteries, which have no direct ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to improve your Morals, without any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of Salvation.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:29913:21"/>
            <p>Secondly, As the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Inſtitution is wiſely practical, ſo it is plain: or in other words, we may ſay, that as the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion appears firſt by its being <hi>practical,</hi> ſo it appears ſecondly by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>plain.</hi> The obſcure anſwers which were given out from the old Heathen Oracles, are now known to have proceeded from the indirectneſs of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning Prieſthood: who,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29913:22"/>to maintain their pretence of foretelling what ſhall come to paſs, ſent back all thoſe who came to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after future events, with doubtful and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Anſwers. And it has been the obſervation of wiſe Men, that when any one affects to be dark and myſterious in his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, either he has ſome indirect deſign in ſo doing, or elſe whilſt he makes an oſtentation of wiſdom he does in reaſity but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his folly.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:29913:22"/>
            <p>Now the Wiſdom of God cannot be conceiv'd to aim at any other deſign in communicating it ſelf to us, than the Information of our Minds in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of good and evil, and this in order to direct our choice; and all Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt of neceſſity be plain: ſince 'tis by things eaſy and familiar, ſuch as at firſt ſight we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, whereby we can be led on to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of matters more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29913:23"/>and difficult: but obſcure and unintelligible doctrines can have no ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect upon us beſide unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable amuſement; and <hi>whatſoever is by the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God laid out of our reach, can be no part of our concern.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Farther, to what end did he give us intellectual Faculties? ſurely not to amuſe but to improve us, by enabling us throughly to underſtand each part of our holy Religion, which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29913:23"/>directly tends to that end, <hi>viz.</hi> our moral Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement: as you will ſoon perceive, if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Chriſtian Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution to its general heads, which are theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, A Narration of matters of Fact.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of moral Laws.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A Revelation of ſuch motives which are proper to inforce this Law upon our minds. And</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:29913:24"/>
            <p>Fourthly, Serious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations to refreſh our Memories with our duty: and earneſtly to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to our practice.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Your Ladyſhip ſees, that the matters of fact contain'd in the four Goſpels, and the Acts of the Apoſtles (<hi>viz.</hi> the Travels and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of Chriſt and his Diſciples) are ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly related, that you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Relation as eaſily as you read it. And
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29913:24"/>Secondly all Laws <hi>muſt</hi> be plain, becauſe they are Directions. Now, obſcure directions are but Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And <hi>Laws</hi> which are dubious and difficult to be underſtood, are <hi>Traps</hi> and <hi>Snares.</hi> And Thirdly, 'Tis as neceſſary that <hi>Motives</hi> ſhould be very intelligible, becauſe their deſign is to work ſtrongly upon our Wills, by convincing our Underſtandings. Add to this Fourthly, That my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical and unintelligible <hi>Exhortations</hi> are ridiculous,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29913:25"/>upon which account St. <hi>Paul</hi> forbad religious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes to be perform'd in an unknown Tongue.</p>
            <p>Now as the four Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels and Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles contain matters of fact, laws, and motives; ſo the Epiſtles contain Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations to Seriouſneſs and Piety, ariſing from the laws, facts, and motives before-mention'd: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> take theſe Books to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently comprehenſive of the Inſtitutions and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29913:25"/>of Jeſus Chriſt: which ought indeed to be eaſily intelligible, becauſe they concern the poor weak, and unletter'd Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as much as the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Nor can I ſee that the doctrine of Chriſt was by him, or his Apoſtles, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd firſt of all into the hands of the learned to be by them convey'd into the minds of the ignorant; but on the contrary, 'tis mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that our Saviour di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29913:26"/>both his diſcourſes and actions immediately to the common people as well as to the Scribe; and in like manner did his Diſciples addreſs their Preachings and Writings.</p>
            <p>From all this Diſcourſe concerning the clearneſs of Chriſt's Inſtitution, you may ſpare your ſelf the needleſs trouble of reading abſtruſe and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious points of Divinity. Nor need you ſuffer your ſelf to be amus'd with the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29913:26"/>pretended deep Speculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of profound Men, when you have the plain directions of a wiſe, and a good God before you, in following whereof you ſhall meet with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Chriſtian Inſtitution is ſhort. True and genuine Religion has always been ſumm'd up, and gathered together into a narrow compaſs, by thoſe who beſt underſtood it. Thus <hi>Micah</hi> (6.8.) ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29913:27"/>of God, ſaith, <hi>He hath ſhewn thee, O Man, what is good, and what doth the Lord thy God require of thee? but to do juſtice, to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God.</hi> And our Saviour ſumms up the whole Law in our Love to God, and our Neighbour. And in another place includes the whole ſcope of the Law and the Prophets, in this one Rule, <hi>Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, even ſo do ye unto them;</hi> hereby directing us
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29913:27"/>to make a right uſe of that Reaſon which God eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd as his Oracle in our Breaſts: to which we may at all times reſort; and from whence we may be reſolv'd in ſuch caſes as concern our duty to one another.</p>
            <p>For as by conſulting your own reaſon, you know wherein you are juſtly dealt with, and wherein you receive wrong; when you are kindly us'd, and when otherwiſe: ſo from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29913:28"/>the ſame principle of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you cannot but know when you deal juſtly or wrongfully, and when you do kind or ill offices to another; this one ſhort comprehenſive Rule, take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for its Foundation the Equality of Mankind in reſpect of their common nature, renders Religion it ſelf a matter <hi>ſenſible</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us.</p>
            <p>For I can feel the wound of a ſharp ſlanderous Tongue as ſenſibly as that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29913:28"/>of a Sword; I can feel the wrongs done to my ſelf and Family; and am as much ſenſible of the benefits I enjoy from the juſt and kind dealings of thoſe with whom I am concern'd; and hereby I am in the ſhorteſt and plaineſt way admoniſh'd of my behaviour to others: and if this one ſhort Rule were reduc'd to practice, the ſtate of Paradiſe would be reſtor'd, and we ſhould enjoy a Heaven upon Earth.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:29913:29"/>
            <p>For hereby firſt all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions for Conſcience ſake, which have occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd ſuch violent diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and vaſt effuſion of blood, would be at an end, becauſe every one who has any Conſcience, would moſt willingly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it free from the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Men in the worſhip of God. To com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Men by Fire and Fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to partake even of a delicious Entertainment, is a ſavage ſort of Hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:29913:29"/>
            <p>Secondly, All Factions in any State would be at an end, if every Member thereof were contented that every one of his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Members who was not an Enemy to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, might, having equal pretence of Merit, enjoy equal Privileges with himſelf.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The occaſions of War and Law-Suits would be taken away. Since nothing but mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29913:30"/>wrong can be the juſt cauſe of either.</p>
            <p>And Fourthly, There would be no private quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, and uneaſineſs among Neighbours; Since by this Rule of doing as we would be done unto, all raſh Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, ſharp reflections, and ungrounded ſuſpicions and jealouſies, which are the Seeds of private Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities, are taken away. And hereby we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a plentiful ſtore of God's Bleſſings among us,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29913:30"/>who will meaſure out his kindneſs to us in the ſame manner, as we meaſure out ours to one another.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhould be both a ſhort and plain Inſtitution, will appear if you conſider the common circumſtances and conditions of Men in this World. For though your Ladyſhip and many more, have leiſure enough to read and digeſt whole Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of uſeful Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (if there are any
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29913:31"/>ſuch) yet the greateſt part of Mankind being neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily imploy'd in making daily proviſions for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and Families, and diſcharging the common offices of Life, cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to any religious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution which is either difficult or tedious.</p>
            <p>'Tis certain, That the whole Life of Man is not ſufficient for him to read all the Controverſies which have been written upon pretence of Religion; but
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29913:31"/>'tis as certain, That God never lays on us a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er task than what he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords us both Abilities and Opportunities to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form: wherefore we may conclude, That ſince the duties of Religion are laid in common upon all, the poor Day-Labourer muſt have ability and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſufficient to inſtruct himſelf therein, without hindering the conſtant work of his Calling. And in all this the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God are made
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29913:32"/>known, by adapting our duties to our circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Life.</p>
            <p>From hence you may ſave your ſelf the trouble of reading the long and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Diſputes which with ſuch intemperate Zeal are always in agitation among the ſeveral Parties of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. Indeed the true Chriſtian Inſtitution being ſhort, it cannot admit of being ſpun out into long Controverſies: And tho' I have read many Books
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29913:32"/>of Controverſial Divinity, I do not remember that I have met with any one Controverſy about the matter of <hi>meer</hi> Religion; as whether I ſhould main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in my heart a high reverence and veneration for Almighty God? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ought to walk before him in Sincerity and Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs? Whether or no I ſhould be thankful to him for all the benefits which I have receiv'd from him? Whether I ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to his will with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29913:33"/>and endeavour to govern my Paſſions, to bring them to a due mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and temper, by making them ſubject to the Law of Reaſon? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſhould be true to my Promiſe, juſt in my Dealings, charitable to the Poor, and ſincere in my Devotions? Whether I ſhould be temperate and ſober, modeſt and chaſt, and demean my ſelf in an humble, civil, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able manner towards thoſe with whom I converſe?
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29913:33"/>Whether I ſhould be hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſorry when I come ſhort of my duty, and ſhould be watchful in the denial of my irregular Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, Paſſions, and evil Inclinations for the future? In ſhort it has not (that I know of) been diſputed whether Juſtice, Benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Meekneſs, Charity, Moderation, Patience and Sobriety, ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd into our affections? or whether we ſhould love God and our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour? <hi>Orthodoxy of Faith</hi> is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:29913:34"/>made the pretence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, but the one thing neceſſary is <hi>Orthodoxy of practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know your Ladyſhip will not be pleas'd with a Diſcourſe upon the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Religion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Devotion have its due place in it; nor ought it indeed to be left out, becauſe thankfulneſs is a neceſſary <hi>part</hi> of Religion, and Prayer is the <hi>Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative</hi> of the whole. A frequent repetition of our
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29913:34"/>thanks for all the benefits we enjoy, preſerve in our Minds the conſideration of God as the greateſt and beſt of Beings; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by nouriſhes Veneration and Gratitude. In like manner Prayer for Pardon of Sin, and preſervation of our Perſons, is a conſtant Recognition of the Mercy and bounty of God. But Prayer againſt the power of Sin, is the actual with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing of our Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from Evil; and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for any Grace is an
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29913:35"/>actual application of our Minds, to attain the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Virtue for which we pray.</p>
            <p>Now although I would not adviſe you againſt ſet Hours and Forms of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, either private or publick; yet I would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther recommend a ſort of habitual and occaſional Devotion, as very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to preſerve the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Impreſſions of Religion upon your Mind.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:29913:35"/>
            <p>It may be obſerv'd that many who are very pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual in keeping to their exact times and forms of Devotion, have fallen ſhort of any viſible improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Virtue. The ſame Pride, Frowardneſs, Falſhood, Covetouſneſs, and bitterneſs of Spirit, have appear'd in many who have been conſtant frequenters of the publick as well as Cloſet Forms of Prayer; as if God had not been in all their thoughts.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29913:36"/>The reaſon whereof ſeems to be becauſe their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Petitions ſuperſede their habitual Endeavours. Men are apt to think that ſince they ſpend in every day ſuch a portion of time in Prayer, they have done all their part: And ſo they leave God Almighty to take care of the event. And this is indeed all we can do when we make our Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions to our Benefactors upon Earth, <hi>viz.</hi> offer up our requeſts to them, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by word or writing,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29913:36"/>and then only expect their anſwer.</p>
            <p>But 'tis otherwiſe with relation to God. Our Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions to him muſt not take off from our conſtant endeavours to perform that work for which we pray his Enablement. And this occaſional Devotion, which I would recommend, is in its own nature a conſtant endeavour after Virtue, as well as a ſerious Petition for it. For it ariſeth from a frequent obſervation of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29913:37"/>our ſelves in our particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar occurring circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; from which obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuitable deſires will almoſt neceſſarily flow. As if at any time I find that I have done an ill thing, immediately upon the diſcovery, I beg God's Pardon, and reſolve to make recompence for the ill I have done. Or if I have deſign'd any evil in my heart, and preſently beg Pardon of him who knoweth the ſecrets there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; in ſo doing I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:29913:37"/>check to its progreſs. In like manner, if I have ſpoken ſlanderouſly, raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or injuriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any one; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Recollection thereof I ask forgiveneſs of God, and deſire that I may not do the like for the future: but on the contrary, that I may govern my Tongue better; in all this I am la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to with-draw my Soul from evil, and to form my ſelf upon a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Virtue.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:29913:38"/>
            <p>Every Night and Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are proper times of leiſure to call to Mind the preſervation, ſupport, and advantages we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the day or night pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding. And this Recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection being accompany'd with thankfulneſs to our great Preſerver, is the actual continuance and carrying on of our grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to God. If I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Pride or Paſſion to ariſe in my heart, ſo that I am apt to put a great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29913:38"/>upon every thing I do, and deſpiſe others: or if I find my ſelf eagerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for any little Worldly advantage, or any ſmall punctilio of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and hereupon I beg of God for an humble Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and a Heavenly Mind; I am herein en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to expel the Poiſon of Sin by its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Antidote.</p>
            <p>We cannot but feel the Diſorders of our Minds, as much as the Diſeaſes of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29913:39"/>our Bodies. And the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of a diſorder'd Mind are much more eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, than the cauſes of a Bodily Diſtemper. For either my Mind is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bl'd for want or loſſes, or it may be for the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of others, or want of a revenge, or becauſe I cannot have my will in what I deſign'd. Upon theſe or ſuch like occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the proper Cure is Devotional in begging God's Pardon for my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content: and being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:29913:39"/>that my will ſhould be ſubmitted to his who has taught me that I ſhould not return evil for evil, but that I ſhould love my Neighbour as my ſelf. This ſort of Solilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quy, and occaſional men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal addreſs to God, is a ſure way to compoſe the diſorders of our thoughts. For the growing power of any Sin is moſt certainly ſuppreſs'd by introducing the oppoſite Virtue into our deſires.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:29913:40"/>
            <p>The ſame method may be uſed as to Sins of Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. A ſerious Perſon will obſerve neglects of common duties, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect either God or Man. He cannot but take notice how much he has neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected his buſineſs, or his health; how little he has confider'd God as his Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Governour and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor: and how ſmall a portion of what God has bleſs'd him with he has laid out upon the good of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:29913:40"/>his Fellow-Creatures. And if hereupon a Man is ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly deſirous to become more dutiful to God, more uſeful to himſelf, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to others, he is therein actually bending his mind to ſupply his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Omiſſions.</p>
            <p>This caſual Devotion ariſing from the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſelves, under the common circumſtances of Life (although it can have no ſet times and forms preſcrib'd to it)
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29913:41"/>will be very effectual to produce, preſerve, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe a true ſenſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion within us. And if you are pleas'd to apply your thoughts hereunto, as occaſion ſhall direct you, this Devotion will ſoon become habitual, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary and eaſy. And its returns, which will be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and ſhort, will be a continual reſtraint from evil-doing, and an actual exerciſe of Virtue.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:29913:41"/>
            <p>This exerciſe which I have been preſcribing is commonly reſerv'd to be perform'd all at once, in an actual preparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore receiving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per;</hi> which is uſually per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by help of an arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Catalogue of Sins me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodically collected out of the Ten Commandments, according to which Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue ſet Forms of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions are drawn up, which the Preparant is to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29913:42"/>take upon content, and without any ſort of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or diſcretion of his own, he confeſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf guilty of all the Sins therein mention'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with all their Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations, though, it may be, many of them were of ſuch a heinous nature, as never enter'd into his heart to commit. And if theſe Catalogues and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſional Forms are read over once a quarter of a Year, or, it may be, once a Month againſt the uſual
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:29913:42"/>Sacrament-Day, the work of Preparation is thought to be well paſs'd over.</p>
            <p>Yet I cannot but think it better to keep a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant cuſtomary watch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our ſelves, and upon the firſt diſcovery of any evil deſign or action, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to retract it within our own hearts, as in the preſence of God, and by mental Prayer, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the occaſion, arm our ſelves againſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the like for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:29913:43"/>Hereby you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge a duty in its proper ſeaſon, which is better than to delay it to a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix'd diſtance of time: for what is moſt freſh in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory will make the moſt lively Impreſſion upon us; but may in a little time be forgotten. Beſides, we are apt to turn Forms into Formalities: And a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral diſcharge of religious duties muſt be more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving than an artificial one.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:29913:43"/>
            <p>And by this your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip ſees the reaſon why I have written a Diſcourſe of <hi>Religion</hi> in general, in Anſwer to your Letter, wherein you wrote only concerning the <hi>Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, viz.</hi> becauſe I eſteem a ſerious well-inclin'd temper of Mind to be the beſt preparation, either for that, or any other of the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, that we may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of 'em with advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and delight.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:29913:44"/>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> adviſes us to delight our ſelves in the Lord, <hi>i. e.</hi> in all his ways and Ordinances. And I cannot ſee why our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for the Lord's Table, and participation at it, ſhould be accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd with greater Anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Mind than our Communicating in any other holy Office; ſuch as publick Prayer or Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. We expect the ſame Bleſſing of God in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of our Virtues
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:29913:44"/>from all of theſe Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces alike. And why with terrour upon our Minds we ſhould uſe any of thoſe means which God has or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd for our good, I do not underſtand. A Man indeed ought to perform every religious office ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and ſoberly; but Fear by amuſing and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting the Mind, is apt to render the Ordinance unprofitable.</p>
            <p>Men ought likewiſe to be diſcourag'd from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29913:45"/>to Prayer, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Communicating at the Lord's Table, with a careleſs, or profane tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Mind: becauſe ſuch unpreparedneſs does harden Mens hearts, and renders the Ordinance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable. Such as this was the caſe of the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> who in celebrating the Lord's Supper, were ſo inconſiderate of what they came to do, that ſome of them were <hi>drunk</hi> at the Lord's Table, as you read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21. and to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:29913:45"/>this their prophane beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, thoſe Texts of Scripture do particularly relate, which affright ſome Men from, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in receiving the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: on this account 'twas ſaid, by St. <hi>Paul, that they were guilty of the body and blood of Chriſt: and to eat and drink damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to themſelves, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lord's body,</hi> Ver. 27, 29. <hi>i. e.</hi> by ſuch a profane and unworthy communicating, they call down God's <hi>Judgments</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:29913:46"/>upon themſelves: for ſo the word <hi>Damnation</hi> ought to be underſtood, becauſe it refers to the <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> ſpecify'd in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Verſe, where 'tis ſaid, that, <hi>For this cauſe</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> of drunken Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating) <hi>many are weak and ſickly among you, and many ſleep,</hi> i. e. <hi>die.</hi> V. 30. Now to avoid theſe <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> he exhorts them to <hi>examine themſelves,</hi> i. e. to conſider with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves what was the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that duty which
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:29913:46"/>they were to perform at the Lord's Table, which duty was this, <hi>viz.</hi> to call to mind the death of Jeſus Chriſt. And this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration is by St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtil'd, <hi>Diſcerning the Lord's body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The viſible ſigns of our Saviour's Death, which we diſcern on the Lord's Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, do prepare our minds to contemplate a divine Perſon, who for his great Charity to the ſtupid World, ſuffer'd the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:29913:47"/>injuſtice, with ſuch an invincible patience, and Heroick Fortitude, as was ſuperiour to the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt malice of his Enemies. Thereby ſetting before us the brighteſt Example of an unſhaken reſolution to do good in ſpight of all Diſcouragements.</p>
            <p>You will perceive, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, by this Diſcourſe, that the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a wiſe, a plain, and a ſhort Inſtitution; the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief whereof was deſign'd
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:29913:47"/>to ſave our Souls from the power and danger of Sin, by ingrafting virtuous ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits in our Minds. You will likewiſe perceive, that I hold it neceſſary to keep a conſtant watch over our ſelves, to repent as often as we perceive our ſelves to tranſgreſs, and by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional mental Devotion, incline our hearts to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the law of Chriſt; and all this in order to build up a habit of Virtue within us. You will alſo
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:29913:48"/>perceive, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the death of Chriſt, with all its cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, tends to the ſame admirable end.</p>
            <p>And if theſe or any other means ſhall work upon you to be generouſly juſt, to bear a good will to all Men, to do what good you can, and to be unconcern'd for the events of things which are not within your power; you will be eaſy within your
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:29913:48"/>ſelf, and ſatisfy'd in your own Conſcience, which is the Dawn of Heaven upon Earth; and you may chearfully Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate at any time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
